[music]
>> Each California Channel Island has its
own heartbeat.
Each island has its own dynamic, its own
size, its own orientation, [music]
its own very intimate personal history.
>> Well, this is the final frontier of of
our continent, at any rate.
>> Well, there's eight islands off the
coast of California. The four northerly
ones are kind of in a line just off of
Santa Barbara here.
>> The southern four islands are more
widely scattered, but to just say that
[music] they're a group of islands is to
completely misrepresent what they are.
They are the trace of a vanished world.
>> I do this interview with a little
hesitation and I'm a little nervous
about what we're doing here. If you love
this island,
for God's sakes, [music] don't come
here.
>> Some days the islands look as though you
can touch them, they're so close, but
unpredictable weather [music] out here
can change that and it has caused many
people to lose their vessels, lose their
lives in some cases.
>> The oceans around the islands are unlike
the mainland ocean. They're remote,
they're hard to access.
>> I kind of think of our California
Channel Islands as our North American
equivalent of the Galapagos.
>> I coined [music] this phrase and I say
it today.
>> Hi, this is Channel Islands National
Park. This is the greatest national park
in America and that's what it is.
>> I've been living here for 22 years
within sight of the islands. Although
I've written many books in this house, I
often wondered what goes on out there.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Ah, what does it all mean?
It's the history of our species, you
know, we're we're we're studying human
behavior at different time periods and
the different challenges that human
beings faced in the past.
>> When people look across the horizon and
see [music] the Channel Islands,
they are nothing other than a silhouette
out on the ocean.
But once one has stepped on just [music]
one island,
you can never look at the island with
the same eyes again.
>> I would love to be able to tell a story
fully in my language, but unfortunately,
my great-grandfather told my father,
[music]
"Why do you need to learn the language?
There's nobody left. Who are you going
to talk to?" So, I start with
sa-hi-pa-ka. Once upon a time.
>> [music]
>> Most days the Channel Islands sit in
plain view of millions of people along
the California coast. [music]
Hardly anyone can tell you their names,
let alone what their natives called them
long before.
Archaeologists [music] know that these
islands have been inhabited for
thousands and thousands of years,
perhaps longer than any place in North
America.
With a human history like that, there
are stories to tell. Stories of who was
there first and how they got [music]
there.
Stories of those who came later looking
for adventure [music]
or gold or just to get far away.
Of one that got left behind.
And some just trying [music] to get back
home.
>> When I tell people that Santa Barbara
[music] and the Channel Islands used to
be down by San Diego,
they just think I'm crazy. They say,
"What?"
So, we're looking here at the four
Northern Channel Islands.
There's San Miguel,
Santa Rosa,
Santa Cruz,
and Anacapa. So, these four islands are
all in a line and they're lined up with
the coast over there. That's the Santa
Monica Mountains. That's all one big
east-west line of peaks.
These transverse ranges are unique.
They're the only ones in the whole coast
of North America.
They didn't start that way. They used to
be parallel to the coast like all the
other mountain ranges,
>> [music]
>> but there's a very good reason for them.
Namely, that they used to be down by San
Diego and they were completely turned
around
110°.
Well, there was this idea of continental
drift in the world for a long time, but
we just didn't know how it worked. But
when I started graduate [music] school,
they figured it out. That all the
continents are really embedded in these
big old plates that are going across the
face of the earth.
Just by looking at the history [music]
of the formation of the Pacific Plate,
we could see when it began to rub
against North America and pull off the
pieces, set up the San Andreas.
>> [music]
>> That's what I worked out.
With just the right tools, I love
geometry. [music] I'm horrible at lots
of things, but I love geometric
relationships and that's just [music]
what plate tectonics was.
This is how it looked 18 million years
ago. The islands here
were right off of San Diego.
>> [music]
>> So, then coming forward in time, there's
18,
12, 6 million years to the present.
So, now [music] the islands are way up
here and San Diego's way down there.
Just got pulled away and turned around.
I just love these islands because
[music] they're so
unique
besides being beautiful.
>> Channel Islands are amazing [music]
for the discoveries, archaeological,
historical, ecological, biological that
that they've produced over the last 150
years of scientific investigation. One
of the wonderful things about the
Channel Islands is that [music] there no
burrowing animals. There's no gophers,
there's no ground squirrels, there's no
earthworms, there's no termites, nothing
that's churning those deposits.
And so for an archaeologist and [music]
a geologist,
it's just a wonderful record because
it's just like a layer cake. You can
look at the different strata [music]
and and really get a refined uh precise
look at changes that [music] have
occurred through time.
Our curator of anthropology here at the
Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History
was Phil Orr.
One of the interesting [music] research
questions he was pursuing was the story
of the pygmy mammoth.
>> To clear, [music] say 20,000 years ago,
the ice age was still full swing. We had
mammoths all over the larger island of
Santa Rosa, to include Anacapa, Santa
Cruz, Santa Rosa, and San Miguel.
Where did pygmy mammoths come from?
Looking at mammoth behavior, we we use
as a model of modern elephants.
And there are documented cases [music]
of elephants swimming over 20 miles.
>> It's believed that this particular
animal evolved originally from the
Columbian mammoth represented [music]
here
that originally colonized the northern
Channel Islands
to what they evolved to ultimately on
the Channel Islands as the pygmy
mammoth. And that species disappeared
right around the time window when Native
Americans show up on the islands.
>> Phil Orr first came out here in 1941.
And so he probably began building this
camp somewhere right around late 1940s.
[music]
His purpose, I think, in making his camp
on this part of the island was because
it's such a hot spot for all the things
he was interested in, the pygmy mammoth
bones. There's lots of great archaeology
here covering all periods of prehistory.
>> I would characterize him as the last of
the bone hunters.
>> I think he's a fascinating character cuz
he did so many good things and he did
some things that are [music]
really off-the-wall and wild and crazy.
>> Well, Phil Phil Orr used some techniques
by today's standards [music] that would
be uh
uh not
approved, I think.
>> He was interested [music] in whether
humans and pygmy mammoths were together
on the islands at the same [music] time
and that led him to look very deep in
the deposits, much deeper than we
usually find archaeological sites.
>> Well, as I understand it, this wasn't
publicized greatly.
>> You know, Orr loved to drive his Jeep
[music] and what he was doing was
putting a road across Arlington Canyon.
They were down here trying to get the
other side of the canyon.
They got mired down and they were
>> [music]
>> extricating the Jeep and they looked up
and saw this femur sticking out of the
cliffside.
>> And carefully scraped around it and
exposed the whole profile to show that
in fact it was intact [music]
in an ancient arroyo that had later
filled in.
>> He found two human femurs
protruding [music] from the sidewall of
Arlington Canyon 37 ft below the
existing ground surface.
>> He knew at that point enough about the
geological relationships in these deep
alluvial beds on Santa Rosa to know that
he was
>> [music]
>> way back in time.
>> And so he got a grant to bring some of
the leading scientists of his day, the
leading archaeologists, and and they
came out here and they were very
critical. You know, they were Yeah, they
weren't necessarily going to buy into
this, but they all agreed that the
Arlington bone was buried [music]
in an original sediment layer. It wasn't
the result of recent erosion. Phil could
not date the actual bones themselves
because
in those days radiocarbon dating would
have consumed all of the bones and there
were problems with bone protein dating.
And he collected some charcoal nearby
the bones which he radiocarbon dated to
about 10,000 years ago. And so, what
Phil Orr did was the smart thing. He
wrapped the original soil matrix
containing the bones, wrapped it in a
plastic jacket,
>> [music]
>> and removed it here to the mainland.
>> I had read Phil Orr's Prehistory of
Santa Rosa Island. That was the go-to
book resource to look at. I read that,
came here, and saw what was on the
island and said, "Orr didn't get it all.
There's an awful lot of material here
that looks unstudied."
And was informed by the ranch foreman,
and I was the first archaeologist to set
foot on these islands in 17 years.
I realized that I had struck gold. The
ranch foreman [music] showed me a
burial. These turned out to be at the
oldest positively dated burial in
California. So, I thought, "Okay, if
[music] this burial at Lobos Canyon is
old, what about Arlington man?"
>> Uh 1987, [music]
I was just newly hired at the Santa
Barbara Museum of Natural History and
this archaeologist from Channel Islands
National Park, who I'd met once or
twice, he came to me and he says, "John,
I understand you have a block of earth
stored there at the museum that has
[music] the bones of Arlington Springs
man that Phil Orr excavated back in
1960." [music] And I said, "Well, I'd
seen something in the basement covered
with plaster that had the name Arlington
Springs written on it, but I didn't know
anything about it."
>> And you led me down into the sub-sub
basement, the catacombs.
>> As I recall, you had [music] to brush
the translus off my back.
>> And we find this flock and bingo.
It's Christmas time.
>> So, we opened up that plaster jacket
[music] and there were the bones exactly
as Phil Orr had removed them. We located
a expert in radiocarbon dating ancient
bone and that was Dr. Thomas Stafford. I
sent him the sample
and a little while later Tom called me
and he says, "You know, I'm going to be
in California. [music] Can I come up and
see you?" And so, we sat in the office
and Tom sat down with us and he said,
"You have the [music] oldest dated human
skeletal remains in
North America."
And and our our jaws kind of dropped.
Lo and behold, these bones [music] were
at least 13,000 years old.
>> And that's really significant because
that's the same age as Clovis. And
Clovis is basically or was thought for a
long time to be the first American
culture.
>> So, we went ahead and and did a a paper
based on that and presented it at the
California Island Symposium
and then it got national attention.
>> But it's kind of odd to have a Clovis
age skeleton on the Channel Islands when
most people at that time didn't think
that seafaring or island colonization or
coastal adaptations existed in the New
World until much later. The time the
idea was that there was an ice-free
[music] corridor in the center of North
America that led people down this sort
of funnel-shaped
tunnel from Alaska [music] into the
center of North America and that people
only gradually spread to the coast over
the ensuing [music] millennia.
>> And it just opens up all sorts of
alternative possibilities and
understanding of how the entire
continent was colonized.
>> It was an ecologist who came up with the
idea of the kelp highway. All the way
from Japan to Baja California, there are
kelp forest ecosystems that have very
similar [music] suites of animals. They
have the same shellfish, the same fish,
sea otters.
>> This connects with the whole idea of a
coastal migration, an [music] ancient
coastal migration where people would
have been using watercraft and going
around glaciers when they encountered
them and working their way down until
they came to California. [music]
>> People showed up on this island 13,000
years ago or thereabouts and evolved
through time and to the group we know as
the Chumash.
>> Ah, what does it all mean?
>> [laughter]
>> It's the history of our species, you
know, we're we're we're studying [music]
human behavior at different time periods
and the different challenges that human
beings faced in the past, different
environmental conditions, how they
responded to those conditions, [music]
how they changed their culture through
time. It just gives us a greater
understanding of our own human behavior,
of our own species, [music] you know, by
studying what occurred in the in the
ancient past.
>> I get the feeling that we've just barely
begun to scratch the surface. We're just
digging in, beginning to learn what to
look for. I personally feel the next
frontier lies offshore in the parts of
this island that have been submerged.
So, there's a lot out here and I think
we're just getting started.
>> Now they're lifting their metal hands.
People in the streets see it now.
They're running toward the East River,
thousands of them.
>> [music]
>> Dropping in like rats.
This is the end now.
>> If you recall that Orson Welles radio
show with War of the Worlds where they
broadcast that and everybody just went
crazy, people committed suicide, people
volunteered for the military because
they actually thought that aliens had
landed. So, imagine a society where
these beings, [music] with this bizarre
technology, suddenly appear in a
landscape where people have lived for
thousands of years.
I can't imagine anything more dramatic.
>> [music]
>> The Indians have never seen ships like
ours or men like us.
They fled in terror leaving behind only
empty huts and warm fires.
>> My people were the first ones to see
the spaceship on the horizon, so to
speak.
>> The first contact [music]
that indigenous peoples in Alta
California had with Europeans comes in
1542 with the voyage of [music]
Cabrillo.
>> Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo was an
adventurer and explorer. [music]
He was a soldier.
He worked for for Spain all his life. It
was a Spanish expedition [music] that he
led and he had been participating in
Spanish conquests and expeditions for
some time.
>> Spanish had come into Mexico [music]
in the early 1500s, had gone through the
process of conquest there,
>> [music]
>> and were finally ready to set their
sails and their sights on something
further afield. And so Cabrillo [music]
came and stopped on the Channel Islands.
>> This was the furthest projection of
Europe into a world that they knew
nothing about.
What he was trying to do,
>> [music]
>> as what Columbus had been trying to do
half a century earlier, was figure out a
way to connect Europe [music] to China.
Now, Columbus didn't realize the
Americas were in the way. The Spanish,
by Cabrillo's time, [music] obviously
did. Once they found out it was full of
silver and gold, though, that
inconvenience suddenly lost some of its
meaning.
>> [music]
>> We always say it's the three G's that
brought people here: gold, God, and
glory.
>> We're here at Spanish Landing on the
shore of San Diego Bay where the
Maritime Museum of San Diego is building
a reconstruction of the replica San
Salvador.
>> One of the purposes in the construction
of this vessel was to help historians on
the East Coast recognize that there was
in fact history west of the Allegheny.
Cabrillo landed in San Diego in 1542.
That's well before Jamestown, well
before Plymouth Rock.
>> It wasn't until 78 years later in the
Mayflower expedition that settlers came
into America. So, historically, this is
actually [music] where America began.
>> So, the idea was to reconstruct that
thing [music]
to house the story, if you will. And
people have been imagining what the San
Salvador must have looked like for a
long time. Mainly though, she's going to
embody [music]
the sense of who we are, our origin
story, as it began with a confrontation
with the unknown. [music]
>> The San Salvador was built 1539. That
was the beginning of what historians
call the [music] gunpowder revolution.
>> The ship, armed with even the very
primitive weapon she had,
>> [music]
>> represented an enormous concentration of
power at the time, as much as an
aircraft carrier would in our world
today.
>> Cabrillo built the original San Salvador
with the aid of indigenous peoples that
were conscripted into the [music]
project and soldiers, many of who had no
experience in building ships.
>> They had a sign-up sheet for anybody
interested in building a boat. You don't
have to be a carpenter, you have to know
anything, just want to volunteer.
>> About 10 years ago, we began to research
what the ship actually would have looked
like, and it was quite a mystery for a
number of reasons.
>> [music]
>> For one, the ship had a short career.
After the voyage to California, she went
on another voyage to Peru and
disappeared with all hands.
There are no plans because ships were
not built to plans in the middle [music]
of the 16th century. So, we had to do a
lot of forensic research into what this
ship would have looked like.
>> I asked how long it was going to take to
build it, and he told me a year to a
year and a half.
It's hard to keep a straight face.
That was 3 and 1/2 years ago.
>> [laughter]
>> We're not done yet.
>> As Cabrillo [music]
sailed up the coastline, it was unknown
how far the land extended to the north,
how far extended to the west. On some
charts or maps of the period, it looks
as though you get about to Santa Barbara
and you're there, you're in China.
>> His little fleet made remarkable
progress given the fact that they didn't
know where they were going,
>> [music]
>> that they were sailing against wind and
current, that they were trying to survey
and chart the whole route all the way up
the coast, and again they were doing it
with 16th century technology. [music]
>> The sailors were pretty brave guys, they
had to be. These These things don't
handle very well. It's like a aspect
ratio of a watermelon.
And it's going to handle like one as
well.
>> You don't get too far north of [music]
San Diego before you start to see the
Channel Islands.
>> Four days later we sighted two islands
and named them after our ships.
Sailing close,
we saw many Indians from the bluffs
calling to us to come ashore.
>> Not only did the Channel Islands have
people on them, they're one of the
longest inhabited places on the face of
the earth.
>> They were well-skilled maritime people
that were getting noted back when the
first European contact came into the
area.
>> When we saw these great ships, my
ancestor as the chief of the village
rallied her people together to say,
"Hey, we have visitors.
Let's welcome them and show them who we
are."
>> It's not a normal thing for people
previously unknown to one another to
have perfectly amenable relations.
And that's not very typical of of
Spanish behavior in this period at all.
But
by the standards of the day,
this was a pretty benign expedition in
terms of relations with the natives.
>> Cabrillo stayed for a little while on
the channel and then he tried to go
further north. [music]
>> It's against the wind and it's against
the current the whole way.
>> And you can't even sail this thing to
weather. All you can do is go downwind.
Whatever the wind's blowing is where
you're going.
>> And he basically got driven back and
then he wintered, [music]
we think, on San Miguel Island.
>> But wait, after all these years,
Cabrillo's back.
Well, [music] not really, but except for
the outboard motor, everything looks
pretty authentic, doesn't it?
>> I, Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo, native of
Portugal, do hereby claim all this land,
which I call San Miguel.
>> We started building the vessel with
notably modern methods.
>> People walk by all the time going, "Hey,
uh isn't that cheating? You're using
electricity."
We always say, "Well, you know what? If
they had electricity and didn't use it,
they'd be pretty foolish, too."
>> We located virtually every piece of
white oak in the country that met the
standard.
>> Well,
they all broke.
Almost every rib that came back down on
the truck had exploded.
>> So, after purchasing all the material
available in the country, we ruined half
of it.
>> Overall, from the very tip of the stern
to the end of the bowsprit, is about 115
or 120 ft. And there were approximately
100 people on this boat
with
horses, cows, [music] chickens, pigs,
you name it.
Sanitation was probably not one of their
strong [music] suits.
>> There were a number of diseases that
seafaring life made you subject to. The
most fearsome of all was probably
scurvy. Hair falls out, your skin loses
its elasticity, every injury you ever
had comes back. So, these guys,
particularly Cabrillo, had lived violent
lives as conquistadors. And when you
start to get scurvy and it goes beyond a
certain point, it's pretty horrific. All
it would have taken would be stepping
the wrong way if you'd had a broken bone
previously, and it would snap.
>> As I went ashore, [music]
my foot slipped on a rock, and I fell on
my right arm.
>> Most people think that the contacts had
relatively [music] little effect on the
Chumash, but towards the end, I think
there was there was some stress and some
strain and there was a
slight conflict at Cuyler [music] Harbor
and I think that's when Cabrillo fell
and got gangrene. Spaniards [music]
probably stayed a little too long and
pulled off some stunts that the Chumash
weren't real happy with.
>> In early January
Cabrillo became ill.
His right arm was swollen and green
>> [music]
>> and his words were delirious.
>> His life had been placed at risk many,
many times. [music] He had lived a life
of enormous adventure but also great
violence. It was just the last risk
[music] in a life of a lot of
risk-taking and he finally found a
gambling he lost.
Cabrillo sailed in to San Diego Bay on
September 28th, [music] 1542. By the
very beginning of 1543, he was dead.
>> It seems most logical that he might have
been buried on San [music] Miguel but
you know, it takes a while for gangrene
to actually kill somebody so they were
cruising the Channel Islands and [music]
that's one of the mysteries that remains
out there.
Be something to find Cabrillo's [music]
grave.
>> We all understand that
the first meetings
throughout this country between your
ancestors and mine were the tragic one.
But those are times that have gone by
and
with this century is the new is the new
time.
This is a new time for partnerships.
[music]
It's a new time to integrate and to
learn from one another.
>> The San Salvador has been very shy about
getting into the water. We think today
[music] we have coaxed the San Salvador
into getting its feet wet.
>> Very proud as a San Diegan to
and we're going to have it in our bay
apparently for, you know, history. It's
overwhelming to see the 19,000 hours of
volunteer time that has been devoted and
you see it captured in one moment.
>> I want to swashbuckle across [music] the
deck and it would fulfill a lifelong
dream.
>> We're trying [music] to say who we are
by saying where we came from. That's a
primordial thing and I confess [music] I
wasn't sure it would work when we
started, but we're standing on evidence
[music] that that does mean something to
some people.
>> If you have a story to tell, [music]
what's the best way to represent it? And
frequently it is with an artifact or an
object, something people can touch, they
can smell.
>> [music]
>> Children spending overnight on this
vessel smell the salt, they feel the the
ocean move.
>> We we learn about our California history
usually in eighth grade and Cabrillo was
one of the names and then we probably
forgot it and then we see it on all of
the streets and and schools and avenues
around the state and now it's going to
put something behind that name.
>> If there was a written [music] tradition
to leave that survived, that would be
extremely interesting because we would
have the other side of what first
contact looked like.
>> [music]
>> What we do have though is the the
petroglyph that we've identified and
documented [music] out in the Jacumba
National Wilderness, which is one of the
most rare works of art in all of the
human inventory of art and that is an
authentic representation of first
contact and that predates [music] every
known image of a recorded event in
American history.
It really does say America began here.
>> [music]
>> My father loved fishing and as a young
girl I used to look out and I would see
this land. I always wondered [music]
what is out there.
Little did I know
that our families originated [music]
from those islands. We always knew we
were Chumash. We always knew that
through our name, Chumamash. [music]
But we didn't know anything about our
culture.
We weren't meant to remember it. It was
looked and frowned upon and even
punishment was happening to our families
if they spoke [music] the language or
did ceremonies.
So I start with sahy paka, once upon a
time.
>> When I'm out at a site, I can't help but
imagine what it was like when people
were living there. And the site I've
been working at just really grabbed me.
I went out there my first year of
graduate school and fell in love with
this site.
>> For Chumash Indians, their cultural
heritage is here on the Channel Islands.
So it's very important for them to
understand their ancestral past.
>> I've been out here for five seasons now.
And the reason that I've decided to
devote that much time to this site is we
really don't have any information on a
site like this. And I think it's a key
to understanding the Chumash and the
past in the Santa Barbara Channel area.
>> And it was only till around the 70s
[music] and 80s that being Chumash and
being native in California was starting
to mean things to people and they really
wanted to know about our culture. But we
had a lot of education to learn
ourselves.
>> I am Barbareno Chumash, descendant of
the last chief in Santa Barbara.
>> [music]
>> I love the science and learning about
how my people lived with their
environment. So as we dig, [music] we
learn more.
I went to school for it and I'm an
archaeologist.
>> This is the largest [music] mound that
still exists in the entire Santa Barbara
Channel area. It also has more house
depressions [music] than any other
archaeological site on the islands. So
I'm trying to figure out why is this
site so different [music]
than the other ones? How many people
were living here at the same time? And
was this some kind [music] of ceremonial
center.
We're slowly figuring things [music] out
and every year we have another piece of
the puzzle.
>> If we try to imagine
what Chumash and other coastal Indian
societies were like on the eve of
Spanish colonization, would be to say
that they had communities that were on
the one hand thriving,
but on the other hand were very
vulnerable.
>> We know that the Chumash were primarily
hunters and gatherers, and the Chumash
out on the island relied a lot on the
foods from the sea, including fish,
shellfish, and sea mammals.
>> We grew up eating a lot of the native
foods. My brothers hunted and fished,
learning from my father, who learned
from his father, who learned from his
father. [music]
>> As rich and abundant as that marine
environment was on the Channel Islands,
there were still things they didn't have
out there.
>> It is said that the word Michumash means
island people, makers of shell bead
money.
For they would purchase large game on
the mainland, the deer, bear.
>> And the mainland people would bring
for trade hides and bones for making
tools and other seeds that they don't
have here, and berries or plants,
medicine, also.
>> First discovery I made when I went out
on Santa Cruz Island that was really
exciting to me
was the discovery of a of a village
where they made blades that were used to
make drills to drill beads.
>> So, here we have the fractured pieces
uh of the purple olive shell.
>> I don't know of any group in the world
that had as many different types of
beads at the same time as the Chumash
did. Here we have the finished shell
bead money.
>> The neighbors of the Chumash compared
them to the Chinese, who at that time,
and probably still, are very
sophisticated in economics.
>> These were complex societies. [music]
They had formal political structures.
>> The Chumash were just experts at
adapting. I think they're highly
resilient.
>> When we look at the density [music] of
people living on the Channel Islands and
compare that to the rest of the
aboriginal California, there were more
people living per square mile on the
Channel Islands than anywhere else.
>> [music]
>> So, the Portolá expedition in the late
1760s led to this [music] chain of
missions along the Camino Real that
formed the mission system of Alta
California.
>> It wasn't until the push northward
[music]
from Baja California to establish the
first missions in Alta California that
the islanders really began to interact
with Spanish on a fairly regular basis.
>> They brought with them pathogens,
plants, and animals. Those three things
began to make enormous differences in
the realities of life for Chumash
[music] Indians both here on the
mainland and on the Channel Islands.
The problem for the Indian communities
was that these livestock began [music]
to trample their fields and their
foodstuffs and their villages. And so,
you had basically three strikes [music]
working against these Indian populations
to the point where they were
experiencing a subsistence [music]
crisis, a food crisis.
>> So, as the people started dying in these
epidemics that came through here wiping
us out by the hundreds, that they needed
more workforce. So, then they started
going out into the islands and bringing
people back to the mainland.
>> As that population begins to decline,
they lose leaders, they lose some of the
elders of the community. And so, you
begin to have a kind of
economic and even sort of metaphysical
crisis going on within these
communities. The mainland Indians, by
1803-1804,
are pretty much all resettled at [music]
the missions.
>> At the height, we had almost 1,800
Chumash living here at the mission.
>> The old trading partners that the island
[music] Indians used to have are now at
the missions. So, what happens? In 1815,
the most severe El Niño event in
recorded history. During
>> [music]
>> an El Niño,
the kelp beds die back and the fish go
elsewhere and there famine conditions on
the Channel Islands.
>> The missions were [music] producing food
and the Indians knew that.
>> All of a sudden, we see this migration
>> [music]
>> of the last people living on the islands
coming to the missions.
>> They didn't want [music] us to continue
harvesting from the ocean, changing of
lifestyles, becoming more sedentary,
gatherers, learning how to farm [music]
with domestic animals during that
transition of the missionary period,
which was more of a prison system.
>> I guess the only good part about the
mission period was that the baptism
records. When they brought the people
off the island, they would document the
people with their native names, the
villages where they came from.
When my great-grandfather was born in
1811, he was given that Spanish name
Juan Day Jesus, but then later as an
adult, he was asked if he wanted that
last name Chumash to be changed to
Marquez. Oh, we'll give you this this is
your proper last name. He said, "No, I
don't think so. [music] I'm going to
keep Chumash."
>> The Indians moving to the missions for
their physical salvation
paradoxically approved to result [music]
in just the opposite. As they gathered
in larger numbers at these missions,
they had that much more exposure [music]
to European diseases.
And so, it turned into nothing less than
a killing field [music] for them.
>> Well, I do think the period of initial
European colonization and contact was
devastating to the Chumash. It did cause
the abandonment of the islands and
probably a loss of a lot of knowledge.
>> It was forgotten for some time.
But fortunately for us the
anthropologist [music] remembered to
talk to people who still had knowledge
and so it was written down.
>> John [music] P. Harrington was
extraordinary ethnographer and
anthropologist and he took notes [music]
and interviewed tribal members up and
down the Pacific coast.
>> Our culture comes from an oral
tradition, no writings [music] and I
really am grateful for that opportunity
to be able to go back and read what
their stories were.
>> [music]
>> After my father passed, I was recipient
of a ceremonial pipe.
And in essence that was the way of
telling [music]
my family that it was my time to step
up.
I love talking with children. That was
some of the programs my father did that
I carried on after his passing.
My grandfather's family were from Santa
Cruz Island and my grandmother's family
was from Santa Rosa Island. I always
wanted to go out there.
>> And as we got closer to the cliffs of
the island, I could see this glimmering
along for miles stretching across the
walls of the cliffs. Well, it was the
abalone in the shell.
When I stepped onto the island on the
land, it was just so amazing.
>> I think this was a persistent place, a
very important place on the landscape.
You can see all of Santa Rosa Island on
a clear day, you can see San Miguel
Island
>> [music]
>> and they came here, they had big red
abalone feast and over time they kept
visiting and the mounds started building
up.
>> There is mixed feelings among [music]
the Chumash people. A lot of them don't
believe in the archaeology or the study
and why are you digging up the past? For
me,
we just learn from it and we can share
things that we've [music] learned
through our grandparents have told us
and we find it in the ground.
>> This is an ashy layer and what I think
it's burned roof fall.
>> What we've learned from [music] some of
the relatives back in those times of
talking with Harrington that when a
person died in [music] the house, the
houses were burnt.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And all the belongings and everything
that the person [music] owned.
>> To feel that ancestry and that long
period of history is very, very exciting
to [music] our family. So, to see some
of the the artifacts that were still on
the ground that a relative of mine may
have made that item was really a
beautiful to me.
>> Can't help but imagine what it would
have been like. [music] And so, that's
what I'm trying to reconstruct the best
I can.
>> We're humans and there's something
natural about wanting to understand
where we came from, how we got here, and
even where we're heading.
>> When we walk on this land here on the
island, we all have this sense of just
really being home.
>> [music]
>> There's eight islands off the coast of
California. San Nicolas is the one
that's the furthest out to sea. It's 60
miles from the nearest point on the
mainland. If you read all the old
historical accounts, they always
complain either about the wind or the
fog. You never see anybody talking about
how wonderful the weather is.
For the previous 25 years, I worked for
the US Navy on San Nicolas Island as the
archaeologist. When I first started
working there, I really didn't know much
about the Lone Woman story at all, to
tell you the truth. But, I started
reading about it and people would ask me
questions
that I couldn't answer. So, I did some
more reading and quickly found out that
there's so many conflicting [music]
versions of the story that nobody really
knew the truth. So, I kind of started
[music] down this path of trying to
unravel what the real true story is.
>> [singing]
>> The thought of being alone on the island
while so many suns rose from the sea and
went slowly back into the sea
filled my heart with loneliness.
I had not felt so lonely before because
I was sure the ship would return. Now,
my hopes were dead.
Now, I was really alone.
>> [music]
>> The Lone Woman has been known by a
number of names. Of course, we
tragically [music] don't know her real
name, the name which she was called by
her parents. But, she's often been
termed the Lone Woman or alternatively
[music] the Lost Woman. She's also been
known as Juana Maria. This was the name
[music] given to her by the Spanish
padres upon her conditional baptism. And
then, of course, [music] Scott O'Dell
chooses a third name, Karana.
>> The story of the Lone Woman is a
fascinating [music] story and Scott
O'Dell wrote this novel that today is
required reading for most every fourth
grader in the country.
>> So, kids, we're going to start reading
this book today. It's called [music]
Island of the Blue Dolphins.
>> When I was a child and reading Island of
the Blue Dolphin, I knew I was
Gabrielino Kiisha descent, but [music] I
was not able to put that together that
her story was related to my tribe.
>> Scott O'Dell [music] first wrote the
narrative and he had some good friends
look at it [music] and said, "It's very
good and you've written a children's
story." Now, this was a surprise to
Scott. [music] He had only ever written
for adults.
>> And it's the story of this girl
>> [music]
>> who ends up being left alone on the
island when she's not much older than
you.
>> Well, one thing we can say is that Scott
O'Dell did a pretty good job of not only
setting the landscape, but also of
capturing what it would be like for a
person to live alone on that island.
Even though apparently he had never set
foot on the island.
>> This upper window was the spot where
Scott O'Dell's desk sat. So as you can
see from this environment, he's far from
the ocean. But in his head, he was right
[music] there with Karana on San Nicolas
Island.
>> I didn't start with Scott O'Dell's
version.
I started with some of the actual
accounts from that [music] time period
first.
I can see most of where Scott O'Dell's
story comes from. He just [music] didn't
have all the the knowledge we have
today.
>> My own research that sort of gets us to
the story of who Juana Maria was
and who her people were is our work at
SNI 25, which is a village site that
we've called the Tule Creek site.
If you read Island of the Blue Dolphins,
the very beginning describes Coral
Harbor. This is the village described by
Scott O'Dell. What he didn't know is he
was right.
>> It's a huge story. It's a big story.
It's not just about this one woman, but
she's sort of the focal point. She was
out there in San Nicolas Island. The
Nicoleño were the
>> [music]
>> brunt of two huge waves of explorers and
entrepreneurs. The Spanish were coming
up from [music] the south and wanted to
colonize California.
>> And it also marks the period when the
Russian fur traders contracted with
Kodiak Island sea otter hunters to come
to the Channel Islands and [music] use
their kayaks, use their hunting
technology to go after sea otters for
the pelts for trade back to the old
world.
>> I do not know what [music] happened
first, whether it was my father who
raises fish against the hunter whose
path he barred. Whether it was this man
who stepped forward with a bale of pelts
[music] on his back and shoved my father
aside. It all happened so quickly that I
could not tell one act from the other.
[music]
>> The lone woman who was on the island
when the massacre occurred, this was
something that we discovered details of
in our search through Russian documents.
There was a murder of one of those
Alaskan Native hunters by the Nikoleno.
And in response, the Alaskan Native
hunters really went wild and nearly
exterminated all the males on the
island.
>> Which results in the population of the
island getting smaller, and smaller, and
smaller down to where there's hardly
anybody left.
>> So, in 1835, a boat named the Peores
Nada, which is often [music] translated
as better than nothing, set sail for San
Nicolas Island to collect the remaining
islanders and bring them [music] to San
Pedro.
>> Right now, we have documentary evidence
for [music] eight people who came off of
the island.
>> When they got on that ship, I'm sure
they had no idea what was in store for
them. And if they could [music] foresee
that, there's no way they would have
gone.
>> She is left behind. We know that. That's
a fact. We know she's left behind. Why
the exact circumstances of her being
left behind are open to a lot of debate.
>> Part of the story is that she went back
to retrieve her child.
>> I think, in reading the various
accounts, she just did not want [music]
to go with the group when they left.
>> She hid, and she wanted to make sure she
was going to be safe. She didn't want to
go anywhere where there's going to be
more conflict.
>> Well, what would you choose as an
author? You know, your job is to tell
the best story. [music] So, in his
rendition, Corina is on board the ship.
It's a little brother as opposed to a
young [music] child. So, at the last
minute, the ship will not turn back
because of a brewing [music] storm. She
takes a dramatic leap overboard, swims
back to rescue her brother.
>> Life on the island, I think it is one of
the real misconceptions that people
have. Everybody always asks me, "How did
she survive? How did she get food? How
did she do this? How did she do that?"
She's abandoned in her own town.
>> Around 1800, [music]
something like two or 300 people were
living on that island. So, there was
enough food.
>> Yeah, everything's here. You don't need
to worry about that kind of stuff. What
you need to worry about,
psychologically, how do you deal with
being alone now?
>> The Island of the Blue [music] Dolphins
is a book that I loved as a child, and
going out to San Nicolas Island and
being able to see the landscapes, smell
it, feel the wind on my face, knowing
the aloneness, the solitude that she
would have felt was extraordinarily
intense.
>> Now, I lived on this island my first 2
years at the park alone, so I can relate
a little bit. I can imagine that over
time she just got accustomed to how to
enjoy herself and provide for herself.
>> I could really get a sense [music] of
what she must have gone through,
although I could never possibly know.
In a way, making that childhood [music]
dream come true just by being able to
somewhat relive and then have such close
physical contact with all of the
archaeology that would have been very
prevalent for her in her daily life.
>> I'm sure after a number of years of
being alone, you're going to realize
that that that's it, you're alone.
They're not coming back for you.
>> I don't think [music] she thought she
was going to be abandoned for 18 years.
>> 18 years, that's a long, long time. It's
kind of hard to comprehend what [music]
it would be like to be alone
day after day after month after month,
year after year.
I mean, at [music] some point, it's got
to really play on your psyche.
>> She could look to the east and think of
hope and family.
To the west, I wonder if there [music]
were times where she was desperate
enough that she wished she could just
get there, you know, to the kelp forest
and just be done? Or did she remain
strong that whole time?
>> Fog crept in and out of the empty huts
>> [music]
>> and made shapes as it drifted and they
reminded me of all the people who were
dead and those who were gone.
>> [music]
>> The noise of the surf seemed to be their
voices speaking.
>> [music]
>> In 1960 when the novel appeared, there
weren't a lot of strong female
characters in children's fiction.
What do you think was the most dangerous
thing that Karana experienced while she
was on the island?
>> One of the most dangerous things was the
devil fish.
>> The tsunami.
>> I think the sea lion.
>> Rontu is [music] Karana's beloved dog
and companion, but before he became
that, he of course [music] was the
leader of the pack of wild dogs who
roamed the island terrifying Karana and
her younger brother and in fact [music]
who most likely mortally wounded and ate
her younger brother. There's also a
pretty harrowing event [music] for
Karana when she's in the cave of the
ancestors.
Okay, what's the first thing you notice
when you look into that cave? Uh Nayan.
>> Um it's really dark and creepy.
>> Looks dark and creepy. Raise your hand
if you would not want to be in that cave
at night.
Myself included.
>> You know, I really haven't put myself in
her shoes, but I was
moved by Cave of the Whales. It's kind
of a
a spooky place. It's right at the edge
of the ocean. You know, if I was the
lone woman, I would have certainly known
about this site. I would have felt the
connection with the people who had
painted those images, connection with
the animal spirits that maybe they were
depicting. That was a moving [music]
experience to be in the the very back of
that cave. Uh it's very sacred site.
>> After a while, everyone assumes, well,
she must have died by now.
Why they make [music] that assumption, I
don't know. It maybe is just a way of
justifying not going back and then
getting her.
>> In 1847, [music]
the Boston Atlas,
uh, I believe was the first newspaper to
report the story [music] of the lone
woman.
>> There was never any real confirmation
until you have, uh, Captain Nidever
spotting footprints on a beach.
>> They'd come out and they'd see a brief
[music]
figure in the fog.
>> They come back to the mainland, they
tell the friars [music] here at this
mission that they found evidence of
someone being on there. The friars
encourage them to go back, and they do
go back.
>> In 1853, George Nidever, who was a
frontiersman and hunter [music] who came
to to California, put together a crew
and took Carl Dittman and four mission
Indians to do two things: to look for
the lone woman and also to sea [music]
otter hunt.
>> They were not on any sort of
humanitarian expedition to find people
and return them. They figured, well, if
there's an Indian here, there's an
Indian.
>> He lands at the island and the first
thing he does is he looks for her.
>> Carl walked along the shoreline and came
around from behind, and as he looked
down through the brush, he thought he
saw a crow. There was this black object.
As he came closer to that black object,
it turned out to be the hair of the lone
woman.
>> During the whole narrative, they're all
very concerned that she's going to
[music] run.
>> He came very consciously because he
didn't know whether this would be the
wild woman of San Nicolas Island or what
it would be. [music] So, he came down
from behind and
presented himself, not knowing what to
[music] expect. Am I going to have a
fight or what? But she smiled at him and
went on her work.
You'd think it was a daily occurrence
that somebody would drop in.
>> According to Carl Dittman, the lone
woman had [music] matted hair,
apparently sun-bleached, and she was
wearing a nearly full-length garment
made out [music] of sewn squares of bird
skin, cormorant skin.
>> Turns out they were never able to
communicate with her.
>> The Mission Indians who are with Nidever
can't communicate with her either.
>> They had to use sign language and they
got her to stay there and they hunted
for about a month or so.
>> I shook my head and smiled at him. He
spoke again, slowly this time, [music]
and though his words sounded the same as
before and meant nothing to me,
they now seemed [music] sweet.
They were the sound of a human voice.
There is no sound like this in all the
world.
>> [music]
>> Well, when the Lone Woman left San
Nicolas Island on George [music]
Nidever's schooner, they proceeded to go
to Santa Barbara.
>> She comes in this whole new world,
things she's never [music] seen before.
She's all excited.
>> I think the Lone Woman would have been
fascinated, [music]
maybe overwhelmed.
>> One of the first thing she sees is a man
on a horse. She's making little little
hand signals as [music] it indicates a
horse, a horse. I try to get everybody
all excited about seeing this horse and
they're like, "Well, it's a horse."
>> Might be like going to Disneyland for
the first time.
>> Well, on the island, the biggest [music]
animal she on four legs she would have
seen would have been her dogs.
>> She took up residence in the Nidever
home.
>> And of course that caused a real stir.
>> This becomes a really big sensational
news story.
And this is another curiosity. Here's
this woman been alone for 18 years.
So, a lot of people come
>> [music]
>> and Nidever actually is being offered
money for someone to take her and
exhibit her as this, you know,
curiosity. [music]
And he refuses to do that.
>> The friars sent for Mission Indians from
various [music] missions to come and
talk and hopefully communicate, and
unfortunately no one could communicate
with her.
>> Maybe on the way here was excited
[music] at some point, you know, I'm
going to see my relatives again, going
to see my family again. And then to get
here and know [music] that she was just
as alone here as she was there. That
must have been pretty miserable.
>> But she lived with the Natives only for
about 6 weeks.
She was unused to having nuts and fruit.
And apparently the diet was too rich for
her.
>> And she gets very, very sick.
Uh and what what she contracts is
dysentery.
>> She died at the Native her home and
given a burial here on Mission grounds
according to the accounts near the bell
tower
>> [music]
>> and that she was administered the
sacraments before her death. And we have
that record on the 19th of October in
that they buried this Indian woman who
had been transferred from San Nicolas
[music] Island.
>> It's it's kind of a it's a wonderful
empowering story of survival, but it's
also very tragic in the in the ending.
It just really
>> [music]
>> rips you up to think that after all
those years on her own, she comes here
into civilization and only lasts for a
few weeks.
>> We do [music] have the marker and that
is a wonderful experience for many
people, not just the Californians who
know the story, [music] but people from
other parts of the United States and
from all over the world who share in the
wonderment of this
>> [music]
>> story of this amazing woman and her
life. It's just really awe-inspiring for
everyone.
>> There was a man on the boat who heard
this woman singing.
And he taught this song to Fernando
Librado Kitsapawit who remembered this
song.
>> She's a tremendous [music]
role model that is channeled through the
character of Karana in Island of the
Blue Dolphins. And [music] I think
that's why so many have fallen in love
with the book. I think what they take
away from the book is how hard life can
be. And [music] I think what they see is
that someone who's similar to their age
survived in circumstances that they
might not have seen themselves surviving
in.
>> But I don't think I really understood at
that age what that meant, what that
story really represented, which is part
of
what we're doing now as a tribe in
revitalizing our culture.
>> [music]
>> This book is about us. This is about
your ancestors, your great great great
grandparents. They're often awed by
that.
>> So now we remember her in this way when
we sing the song Toki Toki.
>> For a long time I stood and looked back
at the Island of the Blue Dolphins.
The last thing I saw of it was [music]
the high headland.
I thought of Rontu lying there beneath
the stones of many [music] colors
and the little red fox that would
scratch in vain at my fence
and of all [music] the happy days.
>> [music]
[music]